Email: verity.hill@yale.edu — Phone Number: +1 984-270-8909 — Github: https://github.com/ViralVerity

Profile

I am a postdoctoral research associate in molecular epidemiology and virus evolution at the Yale School of Public Health. I now primarily work on arboviruses, in particular building genomic surveillance systems for Dengue virus. Previously, I have worked extensively on the evolution and tracking of SARS-CoV-2. I am interested in combining genomic and non-genomic data for practical applications of complex phylodynamics.

Education

2017-2022 PhD, BBSRC EASTBIO PhD programme, University of Edinburgh

From epidemics to pandemics: elucidating the dynamics of Ebola Virus and SARS-CoV-2 Supervisors: Professor Andrew Rambaut and Professor Mark Woolhouse

2016–2017 **MSc**, *Control of Infectious Diseases*, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, Distinction, Highest mark in the year

Research project: Evaluating the use of the Open Data Kit Platform for Investigating a Typhoid Fever Outbreak, Uganda Virus Research Institute.

Supervisor: Dr Robert Downing

Taught modules include: Extended Epidemiology, Statistical Methods in Epidemiology, Pathogen Genomics, Disease modelling and dynamics, Public Health Policy and Designing Disease Control Programmes for Developing Countries.

2013–2016 BA(Hons), Biological Sciences, University of Oxford, First Class Honours

Research project: Does RORgt inhibition affect the autoimmune phenotype of MAIT cells? Supervisors: Professor Paul Klenerman and Dr Ayako Kurioka

Extended Essay: Can social evolution theory help to solve the antibiotic crisis? Supervisor: Dr Craig MacLean

Presentation: Why was the 2014-15 Ebola epidemic so devastating? Supervisor: Professor Sunetra Gupta

Employment

2022-present Yale University, USA, Postdoctoral research associate, Grubaugh Lab

Phylogenetic pillar lead in the Grubaugh research group. I support phylogenetic and evolutionary work in the lab, and am co-leading the founding of a genomic surveillance system for Dengue virus via setting up multiple international collaborations

2020 **University of Edinburgh and COG-UK, Edinburgh, UK**, Postdoctoral scientist, Rambaut Lab

Employed at a postdoctoral level by the UK COVID-19 genomics consortium COG-UK to support the public health response to COVID-19 in the UK.

2019 World Health Organisation, Health Emergencies Team, Nigeria Country Office, Abuja, Nigeria, *Intern*

Over three months, developed and delivered a training course in sequencing, bioinformatics and phylogenetics to Nigerian Centres for Disease Control scientists, wrote a policy guidance document on the use of genomics for response to outbreaks of notifiable diseases and supported normative activities of the team including participating in a Yellow Fever outbreak investigation in Ebonyi state.

- 2017-2020 University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK, Demonstrator & Tutor
 - Teach a variety of coding, genomics and bioinformatics courses which are given to undergraduate and postgraduate students.
 - 2015 Madagascar SAVE, Antananarivo, Madagascar, Intern

Over six weeks, helped to launch a grass-roots NGO, including working with the UNAIDS Community Mobilization and Networking Advisor to adapt a UNAIDS diversity and inclusion workshop for this NGO and to organise and adapt a Training of Trainers session.

Publications

Stars indicate co-first authorships

2022

- 22. Áine O'Toole*, **Verity Hill***, Ben Jackson*, Rebecca Dewar*, Nikita Sahadeo* [and 17 others] Genomics-informed outbreak investigations of SARS-CoV-2 using civet *PLOS Global Public Health* 2(12) https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgph.0000704
- 21. John T. McCrone*, **Verity Hill***, Sumali Bajaj*, Rosario Evans Pena* [and 38 others] Context-specific emergence and growth of the SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant *Nature* 610 154-160 doi:https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-05200-3
- 20. **Verity Hill**, Louis Du Plessis, Thomas P Peacock [and 26 others] The origins and molecular evolution of SARS-CoV-2 lineage B.1.17 in the UK *Virus Evolution* 8(2) doi:https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veac080
- Raquel Viana, Sikhulile Moyo, Daniel G. Amoako, Houriiyah Tegally, Cathrine Scheepers [and 94 others including Verity Hill] Rapid epidemic expansion of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant in southern Africa Nature 603 679-686 doi:https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-04411-y
- 18. Kathryn Campbell, Robert J. Gifford, Joshua Singer, **Verity Hill**, Aine O'Toole, Andrew Rambaut, Katie Hampson, Kirstyn Brunker Making genomic surveillance deliver: A lineage classification and nomenclature system to inform rabies elimination *Plos Pathogens* 18(5) doi:10.1371/journal.ppat.1010023

 Dinesh Aggarwal, Ben Warne, Aminu Jahun, William Hamilton, Thomas Fieldman, Louis Plessis, Verity Hill [and 32 others], Genomic epidmiology of SARS-CoV-2 in a UK university identifies dynamics of transmission Nature Communications 13(751) https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-27942-w

2021

- 16. Moritz UG Kraemer*, **Verity Hill***, Christopher Ruis*, Simon Dellicour*, Sumali Bajaj* [and 20 others], Spatiotemporal invasion dynamics of SARS-COV-2 lineage B.1.1.7 emergence, *Science* 373(6557) 889-895 doi: 10.1126/science.abj0113
- 15. **Verity Hill**, Christopher Ruis, Sumali Bajaj, Oliver Pybus, Moritz Kraemer, Progress and Challenges in Genomic Epidemiology, *Trends in Parasitology* doi:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pt.2021.08.007
- 14. Samuel M Nicholls, Radoslaw Poplawski, Matthew J Bull, Anthony Underwood, Michael Chapman, Khalil Abu-Dahab, Ben Taylor, Rachel M Colquhoun, Will PM Rowe, Ben Jackson, **Verity Hill** [and 13 others] CLIMB-COVID: continuous integration supporting decentralised sequencing for SARS-CoV-2 genomic surveillance *Genome Biology*, 22(196) doi:https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-021-02395-y
- Ben Jackson, Maciej F. Boni, Matthew J. Bull, Amy Colleran, Rachel M. Colquhoun, Alistair C. Darby, Sam Haldenby, Verity Hill [and 17 others] Generation and transmission of interlineage recombinants in the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, Cell doi:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2021.08.014
- 12. Áine O'Toole, Emily Scher, Anthony Underwood, Ben Jackson, **Verity Hill**, John T McCrone, Rachel Colquhoun, Chris Ruis, Khalil Abu-Dahab, Ben Taylor, Corin Yeats, Louis Du Plessis, Daniel Maloney, Nathan Medd, Stephen W Attwood, David M Aanensen, Edward C Holmes, Oliver G Pybus, Andrew Rambaut, Assignment of epidemiological lineages in an emerging pandemic using the pangolin tool *Virus Evolution* 7(2) doi: https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veab064
- 11. Áine O'Toole*, **Verity Hill*** [and 84 others] Tracking the international spread of SARS-CoV-2 lineages B.1.1.7 and B.1.351/501Y-V2. *Wellcome Open Research* 2021;6:121. doi:10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16661.1
- 10. Yvan Butera*, Enatha Mukantwari*, Maria Artesi*, Jeanne D'Arc Umuringa*, Áine Niamh O'Toole, **Verity Hill** [and 30 others] Genomic sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 in Rwanda reveals the importance of incoming travelers on lineage diversity. *Nature Communications* 5705(12) doi:https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-25985-7

- Louis du Plessis*, John T McCrone*, Alexander E Zarebski*, Verity Hill*, Christopher Ruis*, Bernardo Gutierrez, Jayna Raghwani, Jordan Ashworth, Rachel Colquhoun, Thomas R Connor, Nuno R Faria, Ben Jackson, Nicholas J Loman, Áine O'Toole, Samuel M Nicholls, Kris V Parag, Emily Scher, Tetyana I Vasylyeva, Erik M Volz, Alexander Watts, Isaac I Bogoch, Kamran Khan, David M Aanensen, Moritz UG Kraemer, Andrew Rambaut, Oliver G Pybus Establishment and lineage dynamics of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic in the UK. Science 371(6530). doi: 10.1126/science.abf2946
- 8. Erik Volz, **Verity Hill**, John T McCrone [and 27 others] Evaluating the effects of SARS-CoV-2 Spike mutation D614G on transmissibility and pathogenicity *Cell* 184(1), 0.1016/j.cell.2020.11.020.
- Erik Volz, Swapnil Mishra, Meera Chand, [and 31 others including Verity Hill] Assessing transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2 lineage B.1.1.7 in England Nature 593(7858)266-269 https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03470-x

2020 and earlier

- Jing Lu*, Louis du Plessis*, Zhe Liu*, Verity Hill* [and 37 others] Genomic epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 in Guangdong province, China, Cell 181 (5) doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2020.04.023
- Philippe Lemey, Samuel L Hong, Verity Hill, Guy Baele, Chiara Poletto, Vittoria Colizza, Áine O'Toole, John T McCrone, Kristian G Andersen, Michael Worobey, Martha I Nelson, Andrew Rambaut, Marc A Suchard Accommodating individual travel history and unsampled diversity in Bayesian phylogeographic inference of SARS-CoV-2 Nature Communications 11 doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-18877-9
- 4. Michael Worobey, Jonathan Pekar, Brendan B Larsen, Martha I Nelson, **Verity Hill**, Jeffrey B Joy, Andrew Rambaut, Marc A Suchard, Joel O Wertheim, Philippe Lemey The emergence of SARS-CoV-2 in Europe and North America *Science* 370 (6516) doi: 10.1126/science.abc8169
- 3. Andrew Rambaut, Edward C Holmes, Áine O'Toole, **Verity Hill**, John T McCrone, Christopher Ruis, Louis du Plessis, Oliver G Pybus A dynamic nomenclature proposal for SARS-CoV-2 lineages to assist genomic epidemiology, *Nature Microbiology* 5(11) doi: 10.1038/s41564-020-0770-5
- Matthew Biggerstaff, Benjamin J Cowling, Zulma M Cucunubá, Linh Dinh, Neil M Ferguson, Huizhi Gao, Verity Hill, Natsuko Imai, Michael A Johansson, Sarah Kada, Oliver Morgan, Ana Pastore y Piontti, Jonathan A Polonsky, Pragati Venkata Prasad, Talia M Quandelacy, Andrew Rambaut, Jordan W Tappero, Katelijn A Vandemaele, Alessandro Vespignani, K Lane Warmbrod, Jessica Y Wong Early Release-Early Insights from Statistical and Mathematical Modeling of Key Epidemiologic Parameters of COVID-19 Emerging Infectious Diseases 26(11) doi: 10.3201/eid2611.201074

1. **Verity Hill** and Guy Baele Bayesian estimation of past population dynamics in BEAST 1.10 using the Skygrid coalescent model *Molecular biology and evolution* 36 (11), 2620-2628 doi: 10.1093/molbev/msz172

In revision

Verity Hill, George Githinji, Chantal B.F. Vogels, Ana I. Bento, Chrispin Chaguza, Christine V. F. Carrington, Nathan D. Grubaugh Towards a global virus genomic surveillance network. In revision for *Cell Host and Microbe*

Simon Dellicour, Samuel L. Hong, **Verity Hill**, Dacia Dimartino, Christian Marier, Paul Zappile, Gordon W. Harkins, Philippe Lemey, Guy Baele, Ralf Duerr, Adriana Heguy Variant-specific introduction and dispersal dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 in New York City – from Alpha to Omicron. In revision for *PLOS Pathogens*

In preparation

Verity Hill, Toby Koch, Kiet Ngo, Sean M. Bialosuknia, Steven D. Zink, Cheri A. Koetzner, Joesph G. Maffei, Alan P. Dupuis, P Bryon Backenson, Joanne Oliver, Glen Gallagher, Matt Osborne, Sandra Smole, Laura D. Kramer, Guy Baele, Chantal B.F. Vogels, Phil M. Armstrong, Alexander T. Ciota, Nathan D. Grubaugh Dynamics of Eastern equine encephalitis virus during the 2019 outbreak in the Northeast United States

Skills and Experience

Computational

Languages Python, R, bash, MATLAB, STATA

Practical LATEX, Github, Illustrator, Geneious, Prism, ArcGIS, Python visualisation tools including Matplotlib and Geopandas, FigTree, Javascript visualisaton tools Vega and Vegalite

Software Extensive experience in using BEAST and associated packages, especially phylogeographic analyses; Experience developing flexible and user-friendly software in Python and Snakemake; Open Data Kit

Laboratory

Proficient in techniques of cell staining, tissue culture and T-cell stimulation, as well as flow cytometry.

Field

- Yellow Fever outbreak investigation with the World Health Organisation and Nigerian Centres for Disease Control, Ebonyi state, Nigeria We delivered supplies and community sensitisation, performed active and retrospective case finding and helped to organise the transportation of patient samples to laboratories with appropriate reagents. I also wrote the daily situation reports that were sent back to the country office in Abuja, including descriptive epidemiology and statistical analysis.
- 2017 Field epidemiology study with the Uganda Virus Research Institute, Entebbe, Uganda Designed, developed and delivered a pilot study to test an electronic data collection tool for Typhoid fever outbreaks, including formulating and piloting a Case Investigation Form for Typhoid Fever, dealing directly with and training clinical officers in study clinics and performing descriptive epidemiological analyses.

Lecturing

- 2022 Guest seminar for Genomic Epidemiology, Yale University, USA, Phylogenetics and Phylogeography
- 2021 **Genomic epidemiology workshop at CIDEIM, Cali, Colombia**, Applications of Genomic epidemiology and Introduction to Phylogenetics
- 2021 Guest seminar for Quantitative Methods in Infectious Disease Research, Georgetown University, USA, Phylodynamic Approaches to Epidemic Control
- 2021 **ARTIC/CLIMB workshop, online**, Delivered a lecture on genomic epidemiology, and developed an outbreak investigation exercise for participants
- 2020 Guest lecture for Health Geography students at Georgetown University, online, *Phylodynamic Approaches to Epidemic Control*
- 2019 **Nigerian Centres for Disease Control, Abuja, Nigeria**, Designed and delivered a lecture course of three 1.5 hour sessions, with assigned reading, quizzes and accompanying monitoring and evaluation, Lecture
- 2019 **Plant-ID Network, Edinburgh, UK**, *Bayesian Phylogenetics*, 1 week, Lectures and practical tutorials
- 2018 West African Centre for Cell Biology of Infectious Pathogens, Accra, Ghana, 1 week on real-time sequencing and analysis for acute viral outbreaks with ARTIC Network, Lectures and practical tutorials

Conferences and workshops

Invited Talks

2022 Massachusetts Consortium on Pathogen Readiness Seminar, The origins and molecular evolution of B.1.1.7 in the UK

- 2022 **Georgetown Department of Biology Seminar**, The Dynamics of Eastern Equine Encephalitis in the US
- 2021 Annual PQC conference: From COVID-19 Genomics to spread, vaccine and therapy, *The origins, evolution and spread of B.1.1.7 in the UK*
- 2021 **Genomics at Edinburgh launch event**, Reconstructing the spatial epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2
- 2021 **Research Institute for Tropical Medicine, Philippines**, *Genomic epidmiology of SARS-CoV-2*
- 2021 **Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute seminar series**, Large scale genomic sequencing for investigating the dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 in the UK
- 2021 Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Microbiology, Investigating outbreaks of SARS-CoV-2 using civet
- 2021 Edinburgh University Science Journals Society Conference, Genomics and communication in a pandemic
- 2020 **Verena Consortium Lighthouse Talks**, Exploring Ebola Virus Disease Dynamics using a Phylodynamically-informed Agent Based Model
- 2020 **CZ BioHub**, Tools for SARS-CoV-2 phylogenetics to inform public health
- 2020 COG-UK consortium, Civet: Cluster Investigation and Viral Epidemiology Tool

Submitted talks

- 2022 **29th International Dynamics & Evolution of Human Viruses**, *Talk: The origins and molecular evolution of B.1.1.7 in the UK*
- 2019 **Elsevier**, *Epidemics* 7th international conference on Infectious Disease dynamics, Talk: Phylodynamic approaches for investigating Ebola Virus Disease dynamics in Sierra Leone
- 2018 **University of Granada**, European Meeting of PhD Students in Evolutionary Biology, Poster and Talk: Real-time sequencing and its applications to public health
- 2018 **Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute**, *Virus and Genome Evolution conference*, Poster: Examining the drivers behind the West African Ebola Virus Disease epidemic
- 2018 **University of Glasgow**, *Evolution and Ecology of Infectious Diseases conference*, Poster: Examining the drivers behind the West African Ebola Virus Disease epidemic

Additional training

- 2018 Advanced Python for Biologists, Edinburgh Genomics, University of Edinburgh, IJK
- 2017 **Linux and Workflows for Biologists**, *Edinburgh Genomics*, University of Edinburgh,
- 2017 **Infectious Disease Mapping Workshop**, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, UK

Funding and Awards

- 2018 Most Scientifically Innovative Content (Presentation award), European Meeting of PhD students in Evolutionary Biology, Grenada, Spain
- 2017 **£93,000 EASTBIO BBSRC DTP award**, Four year duration PhD programme, University of Edinburgh
- 2017 **Eldryd Parry Prize**, Awarded for highest results in MSc Control of Infectious Diseases, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine
- 2017 £2000 award from Enhancing Research Activities in Epidemic Situations fund, To undertake MSc Research Project in Uganda, Wellcome Trust
- 2015 **£500 Morris Long Vacation Award**, To undertake internship with Madagascar SAVE, New College, Oxford University
- 2015 £2200 Higher Education Funding Council Scholarship, To undertake internship with Madagascar SAVE
- 2015 Academic Scholar, New College, Oxford

Reviewing

Science, Nature Communications, Virus Evolution, Epidemics, Molecular Biology and Evolution, Methods in Ecology and Evolution, The Lancet Regional Health - Americas, PLOS Genetics, Genome Biology and Evolution

Public Engagement

- 2023 **Newspaper interview**, *How worried should we be about XBB.1.5*, Katherine Wu, The Atlantic
- 2022 Newspaper interview, Will we get Omicron'd again, Katherine Wu, The Atlantic
- 2022 **Podcast interview**, Looking ahead to our third pandemic winter, Science Friday
- 2022 **Newspaper interview**, *The BA.5 wave is what COVID normal looks like*, Katherine Wu, The Atlantic
- 2021 **Panel discussion**, Shedding light on the invisible how genomics is helping defeat a pandemic, Wellcome Trust
- 2021 **Panel discussion**, *How UK science leads the fight against Coronavirus*, Swindon Science Festival
- 2021 Podcast interview, The New Variant Drama, The Vax Files
- 2020 Radio interview, 20 minute segment on COVID-19, Radio Verulam
- 2020 **Newspaper interview**, *Genetic tracking helped us fight Ebola. Why can't it halt COVID-19*, Philip Keifer, 538
- 2018-2020 **BioPod interviewer and fact checker**, Edinburgh University podcast about research ongoing in the School of Biological Science

- 2018 Participant in I'm a scientist, get me out of here!, Two week event responding to online questions and live chats from secondary school children about any aspect of my research, research on epidemics, and science in general.
- 2017 **Presenter for Sci-fun roadshow**, I helped to demonstrate a number of small and quick science workstations in schools around Edinburgh to show to children in early secondary school.
- 2016-2020 **Blog**, Explaining topics in virus evolution and public health, aimed at interested members of the general public. Over 3,500 views., https://wordpress.com/view/viralverity.wordpress.com
- 2016-2017 **Presenter for Sublime Science**, Performing science experience for children's birthday parties aged 5-12
- 2015-2016 **Volunteer in Royal Scoeity public engagement events**, Worked with Professor Ashleigh Griffin's research group on two events to demonstrate key concepts in social evolution to members of the general public people of all ages.
 - 2015 **Mentor for Schools plus**, I mentored secondary school children from the Oxford Academy in science for seven one-hour sessions to improve their confidence and interest in science, as well as their GCSE grades.

References

Prof. Andrew Rambaut

Institute of Evolutionary Biology
University of Edinburgh
Ashworth Laboratories, Kings Buildings
Edinburgh, UK
☑ a.rambaut@ed.ac.uk

Prof. Nathan Grubaugh

Yale School of Public Health
Yale University
60 College Street
New Haven, CT, USA
☑ grubaughlab@gmail.com